Jenica Andersen

🔀 jenica.andersen@gmail.com 🛭 in jenica-andersen 😯 jenica-a

EXPERIENCE

Metis Data Scientist

Remote Dec. 2021 to Aug. 2022

- Completed 7-month Data Science immersive program focused on Business Intelligence, Machine Learning, Predictive Modeling, Deep Learning, and Data Engineering
- Developed computational algorithms and used statistical methods to find patterns and relationships in large volumes of data using
- Portfolio contains 7 end-to-end, independent projects with Business application as focus. See Projects section for description of key projects

AIM GeoAnalytics Data Analyst, Senior Geologist

Missoula, MT Dec. 2013 to Dec. 2019

- Project manager, leading projects from inception to timely completion, engaging stakeholders, facilitating client workshops, conducting trainings with diverse groups, and soliciting reviews from clients
- Big Data project collaborated with engineering team to create novel, end-user controlled probability maps. My work lead to the creation of a
- Collected and analyzed diverse data, digging deeper on parameters of interest, and building predictive models
- $Crafted \ and \ maintained \ project \ schedules \ and \ best-practices \ instructions, \ participated \ in \ weekly \ meetings$
- Presented at professional conferences and edited expert witness reports
- Trained on database design and management

Dartmouth College Adjunct Faculty

Hanover, NH Sept. 2011 to Aug. 2013

Stakeholder Engagement

Lectured weekly to students from diverse fields of study, graded reports, instructed laboratory sections, aided field trips and mentored students

Successfully lead real-time drilling operations by prioritizing short-term and long-term tasks and using diplomatic approach to build trust

Sunburst Consulting Lead Geologic Consultant

Billings, MT Aug. 2009 to Aug. 2011 Detailed Documentation

Tableau

PowerBI

BUSINESS

Asana

Technical Writing Public Speaking

VISUALIZATION

Eager to help!

SKILLS

PROJECT MANAGEMENT

Agile Project Management

Database Management

Adobe Illustrator/Photoshop

SUMMARY

Data Scientist with more than ten years of domestic and international

degree in writing and certified in public speaking. Proven track record

and complex problems. Currently co-leading Marketing Committee

for Seattle-based non-profit, and Vice President of leadership team at local eco-school, Meticulous budgeter, Quick learner, Question asker,

experience as a Data Analyst and Physical Scientist. Bachelor's

of successful project management, with history of profitable stakeholder engagement, leading high-risk decisions on fast-paced

and guide project members toward vested solutions, to ultimately get jobs done successfully Developed rapid analyses on multiple data types for immediate implementation

- Published detailed documentation reports with state governments and stakeholders across the enterprise
- Guided high-risk decisions and steer operations with a clean track record of target drilling
- Responded to inquiries and requirements, advised cross-discipline personnel and collaborated with clients

Statoil Hydro

Exploration Geologist Intern

Stavanger, Norway

MatplotLib June 2010 to Aug. 2010 Seaborn

Explored and visualized diverse data using ArcGIS, modeling findings and discovering a lead on a new resource in the North Sea Presented results to audiences with a range of expertise and was offered funding to continue the research

PROJECTS

Deep Learning for Conservation: Classifying Drone Images from Protected Lands

- Classified 21,500 low-resolution drone images as containing columnar cacti or not--data came from effort to develop solutions to automate
- Used python code to create custom Convolution Neural Networks (Tensorflow and Keras) unsupervised ML model
- Custom model contained rescaling, BatchNormalization, SeparableConv2D, MaxPooling2D, GlobalAveragePooling, and Dropout layers and achieved accuracy of 99.3, out performing MobileNet transfer learning model trained on the ImageNet database

Engineering a Data Pipeline for Topic Modeling the New York Times

- Created data-pipeline from inception to operation, pulling in New York Times archive, and modeling topics on streamlit app
- Deployed API get-request to obtain 747,000 articles, converted json to tabular data, stored in SQL database in AWS S3, processed in EC2
- Launched end-user controlled Streamlit App for topic modeling and WordCloud creation

Confident Short Term Real Estate Investing: Building Permit Trends that Investors Should Not Ignore

- Gathered publicly available, municipal data on building permits and real estate values over time
- Utilized Tableau and Google Sheets to join multiple datasets, and discovered construction and cost trends across neighborhoods
- Recommend investors seek homes with unfinished basements in areas with wide range of property values (and other recommendations)

The State of ESG: Using NLP to Illuminate Modern Corporate Sustainability Issues

- $Conducted\ Unsupervised\ NLP\ on\ 1,000\ shareholder\ resolutions\ from\ ceres. org, modeling\ the\ top\ semantically\ coherent\ topics\ using\ python\ pyth$ code
- $Preprocessed \ corpus \ with \ Regex \ and \ Porter \ stemmer, used \ Count Vectorizer \ and \ NMF \ for \ modeling \ and \ clustering, \ modeled \ sentiment$
- $Visualized\ results\ with\ Matplot Lib\ and\ Word cloud,\ and\ demonstrated\ specific\ application\ via\ custom\ Stream lit\ application\ via\ custom\ stream\ via\ custom\ via\ custom\ stream\ via\ custom\ stream\ via\ custom\ via\ custom\ via\ custom\ stream\ via\ custom\ via\ cu$

EDUCATION

Dartmouth College

Master's of Science, Earth Sciences

National Geothermal Academy

Certificate in geologic, engineering, and economic solutions to Geothermal Energy production, with top industry experts

University of Potsdam, Germany

Bachelor's of Science, Dual Degree--International FieldGeosciences

University of Montana, Missoula

Bachelor's of Science, Geosciences Bachelor's of Arts, Creative Writing

Watkins Scholar--Interdisciplinary project work, Riverside Geology, a guide to the geology of the Clark Fork River

CLOUD COMPUTING

GitHub

AWS (S2 and EC3)

Trained in Hadoop

Python

SOL SciKit-Learr

Web Scraping

json

Streamlit

terminal commands

Familiar with R

Basic knowledge of HTML

MACHINE LEARNING

Natural Language Processing Deep Learning

Sentiment Analysis

Linear Regression TensorFlow/Keras

Image Classification

Logistic Regression

VOLUNTEERING

WiDS(Women in Data Science), Puget Sound Co-Lead Marketing Team

Current

Responsible for WiDS Meet a Data Scientist Blog

Clark Fork School Vice President of Board of Directors

2018 to Current

2017 to 2020

Responsible for monitoring budgets, asking tough questions and voting on leadership decisions that often challenge the status quo with genuine passion for the community, its people and its purpose

Toastmaster's International · Club President

Missoula, MT

Missoula, MT

Certified Competent Communicator and Trained Leader

STEMulating Diversity and Inclusion Co-founder of AAPG special interest group